Guide to the Charles Bailey Reed scrapbooks and photographs, 1914-1924 and undated, bulk 1918-1919 RL.01074
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Charles Bailey Reed scrapbooks and photographs
1914-1924 and undated
bulk 1918-1919
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Reed, Charles Bailey
RL.01074
3.0 Linear Feet 7 boxes
Radiologist who served in the U.S. American Expeditionary Forces Medical Corps during World War I; originally from Newburgh, Orange County, New York. Collection contains a few pieces of correspondence, telegrams, military orders, booklets, photographs and negatives, and ephemera collected by Captain Charles Bailey Reed during his service with the U.S. Medical Reserve Corps in France, 1918-1919. The items are mounted in two French-made scrapbooks or housed in loose groups. Materials relate to Reed's time as a medical radiologist at Evacuation Hospital Number One, Sebastopol Barracks, Toul, France. Hundreds of photographs, both loose and mounted, were taken by Reed in the U.S., 1914, 1918, 1924, and in Paris, 1918-1919, and in the Evacuation Hospital camp, 1918-1919. Commercially published photographs depict battle scenes and damage in France. Other items include newspapers reports of the Armistice; images from the Paris Inter-Allied Games, summer 1919; printed items produced for American soldiers stationed in France; and Reed's identity card. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
approx. 1000 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Charles Bailey Reed scrapbooks and photographs were received as a transfer by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 2011.
Collection Overview
The Charles Bailey Reed scrapbooks and photographs date from 1914-1924, with the bulk dating from Reed's military service in France from 1918-1919. Materials include correspondence, military orders, postcards, newspaper articles, printed matter, photographic prints and negatives, and ephemera collected by Reed during his tour in France. Topics of interest include medical care and field hospitals during World War I; medical transport; cities in France and damages incurred during the war; and the Armistice and related events in France, including the Inter-Allied Games, Paris, summer of 1919, seen through the eyes (and camera) of Captain Reed.
Most of the material was mounted by Reed in two large scrapbooks, but there was also loose material found at the end of the scrapbooks which has been rehoused, and there are also many loose photographic prints and negatives. Materials are arranged in series by format and roughly chronologically within.
Printed materials and ephemeral items include newspapersand clippings; military bulletins and orders; information produced for American soldiers stationed in France; souvenir programs; ration cards, coupons, and receipts; and Reed's military identity papers. The newspapers consist of the front page of the newspapers, with a few containing additional pages. There are also a few items in German - correspondence and military publications - of unknown origins.
There are hundreds of small black-and-white photographs in the collection, both loose and mounted in the scrapbooks, most deriving from Reed's medical service in France from 1918-1919. In a few cases they are accompanied by negatives. There are images probably taken by Reed or a fellow soldier, and a large group of what appear to be commercially-made images with captions in white lettering; some of the latter are dated 1914 and depict the British front in France (Alsace, Verdun), damaged buildings (including churches and cathedrals), battlefields, cemeteries, French and British soldiers in trenches and camps, dead soldiers (many of whom are German), and biplanes (including downed planes).
Reed's personal photographs depict camps, soldiers' quarters, military vessels, ceremonies, tourist sites, and damaged buildings; there is one picture taken at Fort Riley, Kansas. The centerpiece of the photographs is a large series of images from Evacuation Hospital No. 1, Sebastopol Barracks, in Toul, France; these show camp buildings, hospital interiors, wounded soldiers in the surgery, soldiers and officers, and vehicles used for medical transport. There is one image of what appears to be prisoners of war marching in a group. Other place names include Verdun, Alsace, Rheims, Paris, Marseilles, Cannes, and Avignon; there are some images from Alpine regions bordering Italy. One group of earlier photos is labeled "Watkins Glen, N.Y., 1918," and date from before Reed's July embarcation for Europe. Additionally, there are later photos taken in 1924 of Pine Plains military camp in New York State, now part of Fort Drum.
Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections at Duke University.
Related Material
Charles Bailey Reed Correspondence (part of the Trent Manuscripts Collection),
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Biographical / Historical
Charles Bailey Reed was born in 1893 in Washingtonville, Orange County, New York, and grew up in Blooming Grove, N.Y. As a young man he studied medicine in an unidentified school, and began military service in August 1917.
Reed's expertise in the pioneering field of "Roentgenology," as it was known then, or radiology, was put to critical use on the World War battlefields in France, particularly his specific knowledge of the assembly and use of portable X-Ray equipment; several clippings refer to him as he accompanied the vehicles and equipment as they were paraded and inspected by military officials in the eastern US and Canada before being shipped off to Paris, along with Charles Reed. He served in the Army until 1919, with a final rank as Captain.
He married in 1920 and continued his profession as a physician. He died in 1973 in Newburgh, N.Y.
Inter-Allied Games; Military hospitals -- France; Military bases -- New York (State); Soldiers -- France -- Photographs; World War, 1914-1918; World War, 1914-1918 -- Armistices; World War, 1914-1918 -- France; World War, 1914-1918 -- Hospitals -- France; World War, 1914-1918 -- Photographs; Ephemera; France -- Photographs; France -- World War, 1914-1918 -- Pictorial works; France -- World War, 1914-1918 -- History; Europe -- World War, 1914-1918 -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Newspapers; Negatives (photographs); Postcards; Scrapbooks; United States. Army. American Expeditionary Forces, 1917-1919; Reed, Charles Bailey; United States. Army. Medical Reserve Corps
- World War I scrapbooks, 1918-1921
  Scope and Contents note
  Two French-made, fabric-covered scrapbooks. Mounted items consist of hundreds of pieces related to the period shortly preceding the Armistice to 1921. There are photographic postcards, including many of wartime and Armistice events, color lithograph postcards, black-and-white photographs of battle sites and other wartime images, souvenir tickets and programs, menus, hotel bills, and a few pieces of correspondence. One photographic postcard is the widely circulated image taken by a German soldier of Quentin Roosevelt's body posed lying in front of his downed plane in France, July 1918; he was the youngest son of Theodore Roosevelt.
  There were also many loose items found at the end of the scrapbooks that have been removed for improved housing and described separately in this inventory. A few loose items remain in their original locations in the scrapbooks.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1918-1921 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook 2 (unbound pages), 1918-1921 (Box 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Unbound scrapbook pages bearing mounted postcards, clippings, and ephemera.
  - Scrapbook 2 (cover) (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook pages, additional (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Two pages from a scrapbook include military orders and various camp bulletins from Evacuation Hospital Number One, Sebastopol Barracks, Toul (from Colonel Gorman); a note from Reed ordering a subscription to Stars and Stripes for his parents; and a special bulletin, October, 1918, reporting that the German government will agree to an armistice as proposed by President Wilson.
  - Scrapbook pages, additional (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Three scrapbook pages containing six mounted photographs. One is of a scene from a hospital interior, with several wounded soldiers in foreground; there are several group portraits of soldiers and officers, and several small panoramic shots of a camp, probably Evacuation Hospital Number One, Sebastopol Barracks. One photograph is a portrait of Majors Shearer and Manges [?]: "Major S. first man I knew in France & who shared his room with me at the Hotel Moderne."
- Loose photographs, 1914-1924 and undated
  These unmounted black-and-white prints typically measure 2 1/4 x 3 1/8, or 2 3/4 x 4 1/2 inches, with a handful of small panoramic prints. Original envelopes with titles of contents are retained with their prints. Many photographs are captioned on the backs. Place names include Avignon, Cannes, Fontainebleu, Marseilles, Paris, Alsace, Rheims, Verdun, and Evacuation Hospital Number 1, Sebastopol Barracks, Toul (Lorraine). The name "Kershaw," written on one envelope of prints, may refer to Kershaw Park on Canandaigua Lake in upstate New York.
  - Allied Games, Eiffel Tower, Paris, summer 1919 (Box 3)
  - At camp, Pine Plains, 1924, July-Aug. [now Fort Drum, N.Y.] (Box 3)
  - Avignon, circa 1918 (Box 3)
  - Boat races, Paris, Versailles, circa 1918, negatives only (Box 3)
  - British front, Lille, Zeebrugge, circa 1918 (Box 3)
  - Cannes, circa 1918 (Box 3)
  - Charles Bailey Reed, circa 1918 (Box 3)
  - Evacuation Hospital no. 1, Sebastopol, 1918-1919, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Fontainebleu, circa 1919 (Box 3)
  - Kershaw, circa 1918 (Box 3)
    Includes views of a three-masted ship, a lake, Charles Reed on board a vessel, a city pier or quay, and an unidentified large mechanical shop. Envelope advertises a business in Central Valley, N.Y.
  - Marseilles, 1919, Feb. (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous--Alsace, Verdun, Paris, 1914-1919 (Box 3)
    Large group includes many small commercially-produced photographs of the front with captions, some dated 1914.
  - Monte Carlo, Italian border, circa 1918-1919 (Box 3)
  - Neufchateau, circa 1918-1919 (Box 3)
  - Paris and Versailles, circa 1918-1919 (Box 3)
  - Rheims, circa 1918-1919 (Box 3)
  - Watkins Glen, New York, 1918 (Box 3)
    Sites of interest include falls, the glen, lakes, hotels, and a downtown; includes shots of Reed and other men in uniform, and several views of an airfield in Beamsville, Canada, with biplanes (opened in early 1918).
  - X-ray repair shop, Paris, circa 1918 (Box 3)
  - Inter-Allied Games, set of published images produced by the U.S. Army Signal Corps, 1919 (Box 5)
  - X-ray repair shop, Paris, circa 1918-1919 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Seven photographs and two negatives, along with their envelope, labeled "X-Ray repair shop, Paris." Subjects include vehicles (probably ambulances or for transport of medical equipment), associated buildings, and men.
  - Evacuation Hospital Number One, Sebastopol, circa 1918 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    16 photographs, 6 negatives, and an envelope labeled "Evacuation Hospital No. 1, Sebastopol." Subjects include the camp buildings, soldiers and officers, the interior of the surgery, parade ground, and a musical band. Many of the prints bear captions.
  - Loose photographs, June 1918-1919 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    There are at least two photographs out of the 24 in this group that were taken in the United States: one is captioned "Glen Springs House, Watkins Glen, N.Y., June 1918," and includes the spa's founder, "Mr. Leffingwell"; the other is a landscaped hillside sign for Fort Riley, Kansas (Medical Dept.?). The other photographs are views of Evacuation Hospital Number One, Sebastopol Barracks, Toul; subjects include interior shots of surgery, a recovery ward, camp buildings, and soldiers. There is also a halftone reproduction card of a photograph taken in the ship's medical operating room, circa 1918-1919. According to the U.S. Naval Historical Center, this image was published as one of ten photographs in a "Souvenir Folder" of views of the USS Sierra. According to military papers in the collection, Reed returned to the U.S. aboard this ship.
- Printed materials, papers, and ephemera, 1917-1919 and undated
  Charles Reed mounted many printed materials and ephemera in his scrapbooks, most but not all of them collected during his Medical Corps training and American Expeditionary Forces services in France. These loose items were housed separately from the scrapbook albums in Boxes 1-2.
  Ephemera includes postcards; Reed's military identity papers and AEF identity card; a few German items, including German publications and two letters from Berlin, of unknown origin; and French ration cards, receipts, and coupons.
  Printed materials chiefly comprise military orders; typed bulletins and instructions; news clippings, chiefly rlated to Reed's work with portable radiology equipment; souvenir programs and booklets; and tourist guides for soldiers in France during World War I. One set of materials documents elaborate shows and games held by the United States and Allies in Paris in 1919, as U.S. troops prepared to return home.
  These loose materials are similar to Scrapbook Series materials mounted on pages, especially military papers and news clippings.
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 1)
    - Letters, in German, from Berlin, 1918, April 21 and Aug. 5 (Box 4)
    - APM [Assistant Provost Marshal?] Paris, registration coupons, 1918 (Box 4)
    - French currency, 1919 (Box 4)
    - French ration cards, 1919 (Box 4)
    - German Army postal service letter, blank, undated (Box 4)
    - German Army watch book, undated (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 4)
    - Instructions for Troops, 1917, December 28 (Box 4)
    - B. van Vorst, France, Our Ally, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Seeing Nancy. A Guide for Americans, with Map, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Amerika und der Weltkrieg, circa 1915 (Box 4)
      "America and the War."
    - Das Machinen-Gewehr 08. Lehrbuch für Unteroffiziere und Mannschaften, circa 1917-1919 (Box 4)
      An instructional book for German soldiers about a type of rifle.
    - Grand-Duchy of Luxemburg, 1910s? (Box 4)
    - Pages of American Glory, 1919 (Box 4)
      Booklet published by Michelin Tire Company, giving tribute to American troops in France.
    - Paris, Monumental Métropolitain, circa 1918-1919 (Box 4)
    - Roman Treves, Its History & Sights, undated (Box 4)
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 2)
    - Military orders, 1917 (Box 4)
    - Railway dining car receipt, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Newspaper clipping, 1919, May 23 (Box 4)
    - Automobile check, Inter-Allied Games, 1919 (Box 4)
    - Racing-club de France ticket, undated (Box 4)
    - Inter-Allied Games, Pershing Stadium, Joinville-le-Pont, Paris, 1919, July 4 (Box 4)
    - Le Sportif, Revue Hebdomadaire de Critique Sportive, 1919, July 19 (Box 4)
    - Who Can Tell? 88th Division Show, Paris, 1919 (Box 4)
  - Postcards, circa 1914-1919
    These four postcards were found in Scrapbook 1, and were separated for preservation purposes.
    - Cannes (Box 4)
    - Cornell University (Box 4)
    - Rouen (Box 4)
    - Verdun (Box 4)
  - Printed materials and papers, additional, 1918-1919
    Consists of a few pieces of correspondence with family; military orders, including one from April 1918 giving Charles Reed's embarkation order; lists of equipment required and suggested; various military orders and bulletins; a printed message from General Pershing following the armistice; and news clippings related to Reed's work with portable radiology services, which was put to use at the European front.
    - Military papers and orders, correspondence, and telegrams (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Military papers and clippings (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Ephemera, additional, 1918-1919
    Consists of a few pieces of ephemera, including a card from a Thanksgiving Dance at the Evacuation Hospital, and Charles Reed's war identity papers and American Expeditionary Forces identity card, 1918.
    - Cards and identity papers (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Newspapers, 1918-1919
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 1)
    - La Liberté, 1918, November 11 (Box 5)
    - American Daily Mail, 1918, November 17 (Box 5)
    - New York Herald, European edition, 1918, Nov. 20, 21, 29, 30; Dec. 3, 4, 15 (Box 5)
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 2)
    - New York Herald, European edition, 1919, June 24, July 11 (Box 5)
    - Excelsior, 1919, August 8 (Box 5)
    - Unidentified newspaper, 1919, Oct. 19 (Box 5)